<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation containing the manner of the solemnities at the election and coronation of Ferdinand the Emperour, in Francford the 30. of August last past, 1619 With other occurrences in Bohemia, and diuers parts of Germany, for three moneths last past.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00682</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105587</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841314</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841314</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5889</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00682)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5889)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation containing the manner of the solemnities at the election and coronation of Ferdinand the Emperour, in Francford the 30. of August last past, 1619 With other occurrences in Bohemia, and diuers parts of Germany, for three moneths last past.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Elde] for Robert Mylbourne, and are to be solde at the great south-dore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ferdinand --  II, --  Holy Roman Emperor, 1578-1637 --  Coronation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bohemia (Czech Republic) --  History --  1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5889:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5889:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION CONTAINING THE MANNER OF THE Solemnities at the Election and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Emperour, in <hi>Francford</hi> the 30. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt paſt, 1619. <hi>WITH</hi> Other Occurrences in BOHEMIA, <hi>and diuers parts of</hi> GERMANY, for three Moneths laſt paſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for ROBERT MYLBOVRNE, and are to be ſolde at the great South-dore of <hi>Paules.</hi> 1620.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:5889:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5889:2"/>
            <head>THE MANNER OF the Solemnities at the Election and Coronation of <hi>Fardinand</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, in <hi>Francford Auguſt</hi> 30. 1619. With other occurrences in <hi>Bohemia</hi> and diuers <hi>parts of Germany for three moneths laſt paſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Earle of <hi>Thorne</hi> (after hee had renewed his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> and diſpatched his affaires in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauia,</hi> according to his harts deſire) remoued his Campe from thence, and paſſed into the lower <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting ſome certaine places and townes by the way, laid ſiege againſt <hi>Laba,</hi> which refuſed to giue him admittance becauſe it was fortified with a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon.</p>
            <p>The Proteſtant States, ſeeing that they could not hitherto make any full agreement with the Romiſh Catholiques, and that they had ſpent all the time
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5889:3"/>in vaine, ſent their embaſſadours vnto him, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of him what reaſon hee had to enter that country with ſo great an army: and to requeſt him, that, ſeeng they had done nothing which might offend the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> hee would lead away his Forces from thence againe. For the reaſon why hitherto they had returned no anſwer to the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which were ſent from the <hi>Bohemians</hi> the fifth of March, was, becauſe that the Romiſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique States, day by day, deferred to giue their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegoricall and reſolute anſwer to the principall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles and clauſes of thoſe Letters; and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding had alwayes made fayre ſhew of a friendly agreement and peaceable end. Howeuer, albeit they ſaw that their hope hereof was fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, yet they were not againſt the much-deſired League, but were rather glad of it: and the rather, for that they called to minde, how that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Matthias</hi> anſwered the States at <hi>Budwitz</hi> in the yeare 1614. that they ſhould ſend their Legates or Embaſſadors to the Parliament which was to be holden at <hi>Prage</hi> in the yeare 1615. and then and there ſhould enter a Treaty concerning the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of that League. Wherefore they gaue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and authoritie to their Deputies or Legates, to renew that League; prouided, that it were not repugnant to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and the States and Religion of the Romiſh Catholiques. This Embaſſie by fiue ſelected and choſen out of euery State, was performed.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:5889:3"/>
            <p>A while after there came to the Camp, certaine Embaſſadours of the Romiſh catholike States, and Earle <hi>Buchem</hi> being their Spokeſman, they ſay that they neuer did any thing that might aggrieue ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Earle of <hi>Thorne,</hi> or any others of the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemians:</hi> and that they did very carefully maintaine and preſerue peace. Wherefore they requeſt that he would be pleaſed to ſpare them, and to diſlodge his Campe from before <hi>Laba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching the Confederation and League betwixt the Proteſtants and them; It was true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that the Proteſtant States and they had not yet drawne to a full concluſion in all things; yet, foraſmuch as the points of difference betwixt them were but ſmall, they were in good hope that very ſhortly a good end and agreement ſhould be made betwixt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thorne</hi> making anſwer, ſaid vnto them; That the <hi>Bohemians</hi> by maine neceſſity were conſtrained to doe what they did: and for his part, That he would not willingly vndertake any thing againſt any man without cauſe: but his deſire was, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue all hoſtile Forces, and to driue away the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my though hee were at <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> That hee came into that Prouince to preſerue peace and tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to relieue and ayd the oppreſſed; for hee would faine haue it ſo, that hereafter the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants and Romiſh Catholiques ſhould walke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand in hand as equals one to another in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reſpect. That heretofore the Romiſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5889:4"/>haue had the ſuperiority and preheminence, but againſt good reaſon; for the Proteſtants were as honeſt men as the Romiſh Catholiques, and therefore hee would no longer ſuffer that theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kept vnder and oppreſſed, the Romiſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques (like oyle in water) ſhould ſwimme aloft: for he would haue an equalitie kept amongſt them, without any reſpect had to one Religion or other; and looke what priuiledges were granted to the one ſide, the ſame ſhould be permitted to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſo a conſtant and perpetuall peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them might be made: And that whoſoeuer ſhould be their King and Prince, hee might be ſafe from the treacheries and commotions of the <hi>Cleſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians,</hi> &amp; ſo might gouerne the weale publique with greater quietneſſe and honour. For his owne part, hee tooke no care whence or from whom he ſhould receiue prouiſion, mony or aid to maintaine his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. He had reſigned himſelfe vp to God, and made prayers to him, that he would further and proſper this his honeſt and truly Chriſtian purpoſe, and grant vnto him power and ſtrength fitting and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for him. That he tels them the truth, That he would neuer haue made any attempt againſt <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> but that he found it fortified with a Gariſon, and that they themſelues were the cauſes why hee did beſiege it. For hee had giuen notice to Earle <hi>Trauſtam,</hi> that when hee found no Gariſon, nor any reſiſtance, there the people ſhould not need to feare any danger by his comming.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:5889:4"/>
            <p>When the Legates had heard him ſpeake thus, they made anſwer, that they would deale with <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand,</hi> &amp; do their beſt endeauours, that both <hi>Laba</hi> and other places in that Prouince might bee quit and cleared of Souldiers.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Thorne</hi> gaue his word that on condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that Gariſon might be remoued, the gates of the Citie ſet open, and hereafter the Citie fenced with a Gariſon of Proteſtants, and not with ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, hee would not attempt any thing further againſt that place: and ſo he diſmiſſed them.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the Lords directors held a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation, that if a treaty of peace were to be made, vpon what condition it were to be entertained: and they concluded &amp; decreed it altogether neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That all Proteſtants whatſoeuer (as well States as inferiours) throughout the whole Kingdome, whether they dwelt vnder a Romiſh catholike or an Euangelicall Magiſtrate, by vertue of a charter granted vnto them by the Emperour <hi>Rodolphus,</hi> in point of Religion; (it being mutually couenanted on both ſides) ſhould enioy the benefite of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creteſt conſultations in the Parliament, and Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all confirmations, and it ſhould be lawfull for them as well as for the <hi>Sileſians</hi> &amp; others in other places to erect and ſet vp Schooles; all ſuch acts, decrees, prouiſo's, made heretofore to the contrary, either by <hi>Ferdinand</hi> or by them that are <hi>Sub vnâ,</hi> being declared to be voyd and of none effect.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:5889:5"/>
            <p n="2">2 That the Proſcription and the baniſhing of the Ieſuits out of the Kingdome, ſhould be ratified and made ſure and firme for euer: ſo that it ſhall neuer be lawfull for them to returne into that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vnder pretence of any order whatſoeuer. That their Colledges and all their goods ſhould be confiſcate and adiudged to the publique good of the States, and that their priuiledges ſhould be razed out of publique Records.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That their Confederations and Leagues made with the people of <hi>Hungaria, Auſtria, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauia,</hi> and of both the <hi>Luſatia's</hi> ſhould bee ratified and confirmed.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That the Matter of Defence ſhould be defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red till the generall Aſſembly of thoſe Prouinces.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That it ſhould be lawfull to ordaine and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt Aſſemblies of States in diuers Territories, after the ancient manner.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That the hereditary Leagues with the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and other neighbour Princes, ſhould bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed.</p>
            <p n="7">7 That the Baniſhing and proſcription of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine men out of the Kingdome, the remouing of them from the publique Offices, ſhould bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and firme.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:5889:5"/>
            <p>To theſe ſeuen articles, the Directors after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards added diuers others which they thought needfull for the Kingdome and the prouinces: as namely,</p>
            <p n="1">1 That, that decree where the deceaſed Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour did giue to the biſhop of <hi>Prage Ius patronatus,</hi> the aduowſon and patronage, to preſent Prieſts to all Churches, is repugnant to his Maieſties Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and therefore let it be abrogated, and let the power be giuen to the conſiſtory of <hi>Prage</hi> to confer thoſe benefices vpon ſuch Paſtors as are addicted to that religion, which is principally profeſſed in that Pariſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Seeing that the Subiects dwelling not only in the Emperours dominions, but alſo in other ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall or ſecular iuriſdictions, (both parties being agreed) by the Emperours charter, had had pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authority hitherto to erect Churches and Schooles, let them ſtill retaine and keepe the ſame hereafter, and let theſt <hi>Cloſtergrabiens,</hi> whoſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was demoliſhed by the Biſhop, make vſe of ſome other temple in the City, vntill their owne be reedified.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Let the <hi>Burnauiens</hi> hereafter quietly and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly poſſeſſe their owne Church.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The Churches in the City of <hi>Prage</hi> (which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5889:6"/>haue beene built ſince his Maieſties Charter was obtained) as namely the Church of the holy Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in the leſſer towne; and the Churches of our Sauiour, and of <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Iude,</hi> with the Chappell adioining to it, in the old towne, let them for euer be left in the power of them which are <hi>Sub vtrâ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</hi> and by whom they were built: and the next Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment let them be regiſtred in the publike recordes.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Foraſmuch as the vniuerſity of <hi>Prage</hi> and all the goods appertaining vnto it, were giuen by the Emperour <hi>Rodolphus</hi> to the States <hi>Sub vtrâ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</hi> Therfore let them ſtill haue power either to beſtow ſome thing of their owne, or to exact of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects any thing whereby that vniuerſity and other Churches may be ſuſtained, and that which is ſo collected, let it be kept vpon record, and required of the defenders as well as other publike contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Subiects.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Let not any other ſpirituall orders beſides thoſe which are in the kingdome already, be brought in either by the King, or by thoſe which are <hi>Sub vnâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 Let not the Commiſſaries which are wont to be ſent to the Parliament by the King: let them not dwell too long vpon the Kings propoſition, but ſpeedily require an anſwer from the States.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Let the States in the Parliament conferre their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5889:6"/>voyces together; and after they haue collected their voyces, let them giue vp their anſwers by one either ſeuerally or generally: neither let the Kings Councellers ſunder and ſeparate themſelues from the States, but let them alſo giue their beſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and aduice for the common good.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Let it not be lawfull to except againſt the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the States in Parliaments: neither let the States be bound to admit any reply, or to accept any other concluſion, if perhaps after their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture any ſuch concluſion be made of any.</p>
            <p n="10">10 And let not the Parliament be continued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue 14. dayes, vnleſſe it be by a peculiar conſent of the States.</p>
            <p n="11">11 When the chiefe Chancelor of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes propoundeth any thing to the King, let an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Chancelor be preſent, and haue notice giuen him of the ſame.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Such as are to be Secretaries and Clarkes of the Chancery, let them be honeſt men, and addic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Religion <hi>Sub vtrâ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</hi> after the vſuall and accuſtomed manner in former times.</p>
            <p n="13">13 In the next Parliament, let there be a conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation held, about renewing the Hereditary leagues with the Electors and other neighbour countries.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:5889:7"/>
            <p n="14">14 That which hath been already concluded, in the laſt aſſembly, concerning ſome perfidious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whereof ſome were to be baniſhed the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and ſome to be barred from publike offices: let it remaine firme and ratified.</p>
            <p n="15">15 Hereafter let none of the Kings Lieutenants in the townes of <hi>Prage</hi> be ſuſteyned or maintained, neither let the Kings Iudges haue place either in the townes of <hi>Prage,</hi> or in any others.</p>
            <p n="16">16 And ſeeing that by commandement of the States, the Directors and exactors of contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue runne into a great deale of debt, in defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and preſeruing the Kingdome from the enemy, and in paying the Souldiers their ſtipends (the Directors in the meane while being wiſe enough to ſaue themſelues harmleſſe) Therefore let the goods of ſuch as were cauſes of that war (whether they be fled out of the Kingdome, or ſtill remaine in it) be confiſcated, and adiudged to the paiment of thoſe debts.</p>
            <p n="17">17 In like manner, let the Kings goods be ſold (alwayes excepting thoſe goods of the King which are inſerted into publique records, and can neuer be alienated) Let the Kings goods be ſould ſeeing they were redeemed with other mens mony, and that many therefore were conſtrained to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage their faith and credit: and let the mony which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5889:7"/>is collected thence be imployed to the payment of the Kings debts, and towards the repayring of their dammages and loſſes, whoſe Houſes and goods were pillag'd and burnt vp by the Kings Souldiers.</p>
            <p n="18">18 Such Church goods as vpon the vrgency of extreame neceſſity, haue beene laid to pawne or ſold outright, let them not be redeemed at all; but let more of them be ſold away, yet with this cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that prouiſion be made that the ſpirituall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be honeſtly maintained.</p>
            <p n="19">19 Let not the chamber of <hi>Bohemia</hi> be ſubiect to the Kings chamber, nor doe ſeruice to it in further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the decrees thereof.</p>
            <p n="20">20 Let the walles be reedified about the townes of <hi>Prage,</hi> and let all forraigne Eccleſiaſticall lawes be ſubiect to their iuriſdiction.</p>
            <p n="21">21 The <hi>Prage</hi> townes and other townes which haue a third free ſtate, let them not hereafter be called any more by the royall name of Chamber goods, as heretofore in publique records, (wee know no reaſon why) they were ſtiled and enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled.</p>
            <p n="22">22 What ſhall be done concerning thoſe two Cities in the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> namely <hi>Pilſna</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:5889:8"/>and <hi>Budwitz,</hi> let it be conſulted vpon.</p>
            <p n="23">23 Touching money which ſhall accrew by bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, let the halfe of it be imployed vpon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing the wals of the City, and vpon the <hi>Prage</hi> Townes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pilſna, Budwitz,</hi> and <hi>Gretſna,</hi> let them be giuen to the State <hi>ab vtra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</hi> that in them they may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide ſufficient Armories, without which our bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of Defence cannot come to any good.</p>
            <p n="24">24 But to whoſe truſt theſe Armories are to be committed, and what coſts and charges are need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for prouiding and ſtoring vp armes therein, let conſultation be had hereafter.</p>
            <p>At this time there was a Parliament holden at <hi>Vratiſlavia</hi> by the Princes and the States of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſia:</hi> The King ſent to it one <hi>Otto Melander</hi> a noble Heroicall Gentleman, and one of his Councell: who from the Prince of <hi>Lignitz,</hi> in the name of the reſt of the Princes and States, brought backe this anſwere, <hi>viz:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They ſay, that by relation of the Noble and Honourable Parſonage <hi>Otto Melander,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by his Maieſties Royall Letters, which hee deliuered vnto them, they were giuen to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that <hi>Ferdinand</hi> hath determined, ſince the Emperour <hi>Matthias</hi> is now deceaſed, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the gouernment of the Kingdome, and to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5889:8"/>confirme vnto theſe Princes and Countries, all lawes, rights, and priuiledges, as well gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall as ſpeciall, all Grants and Cuſtomes, euen the <hi>Maieſtatis Diploma,</hi> the Charters of State, which were granted by his Predeceſſours, the Kings of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> by <hi>Ferdinand, Maximilian, Rodolphus</hi> and <hi>Matthias:</hi> and that hee is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined not onely to confirme whatſoeuer hath beene granted by his Predeceſſors, but alſo to ſend his Confirmation vnto them: or if at this time it be full of danger to ſend ſuch Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet at leaſt hee will accept whatſoeuer ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall priuiledges any of the Prouinces can ſhew for themſelues. That looke what diſſentions and diſagreements there be betwixt the Romiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques and Proteſtants, he is purpoſed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound them.</p>
            <p>That hee would in theſe places confirme the Office of the King, and accept from him the Oath of Allegiance: and did hope that by this meanes it would come to paſſe, that (ſeeing hee promiſed moreouer to take vpon him, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the Emperours debts which hee owed in the Prouinces of <hi>Sileſia</hi>) the States of <hi>Sileſia</hi> would not onely pay ſuch Contributions as they had formerly promiſed, but alſo would performe all other duties and offices which were due vnto him: That in ſo doing hee himſelfe alſo might haue cauſe to declare and ſhew his fatherly loue and affection vnto them ſtill more and more:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5889:9"/>And that alſo, the States of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to whom in like manner he had already ſent the Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Priuiledges, might thereby take occaſion to ſettle themſelues to due obedience, that ſo all troubles being compoſed, and warres ended, the Kingdome might enioy her former peace and tranquilitie.</p>
            <p>But as heretofore it gaue them great content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Emperour <hi>Matthias</hi> was pleaſed to deuiſe a way how his Kingdomes and Countries might be prouided of one to be their head, and to ſucceed him after his death; and that ſo all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of warres and ſeditions being cut off, peace and tranquility might be preſerued and continued in the Kingdome: So alſo they called to minde, when that Succeſſion was giuen to <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what conditions they accepted it, and what promiſes they receiued from him; and what they on the other ſide were bound to performe vnto him: and ſo they wiſh with all their hearts, that <hi>Matthias</hi> his departure had hapned at ſuch time, as all things being in peace, they might quietly vſe and enioy their piuiledges and immunities, and <hi>Ferdinand</hi> might obtaine the wiſhed end of his Succeſſion with greateſt facilitie: for ſo nothing could haue hindered them, but that vpon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of the Letters of Confirmation of their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and ſpeciall priuiledges, they had forthwith accepted him for their King, and had performed vnto him all ſuch offices as were due.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:5889:9"/>
            <p>But howſoeuer it be, they are exceeding glad, that he remembring his promiſe made vnto them, is deſirous to put it in execution. But they doubt not, but that <hi>Ferdinand</hi> will ſet before his eyes, how lamentable and confuſed the ſtate of thoſe Countries is; and that the combuſtion is now ſpread ſo farre, and growne ſo vehement, that it cannot without great difficultie and danger be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed and ſuppreſſed: and that hee will be pleaſed to take into his conſideration, how farre theſe times are altered from thoſe wherein his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> was made:</p>
            <p>As namely, that now the publique peace and quiet is diſturbed, all the Country embroyled with warres, their Townes ſacked and ſpoyled, and euery place fraught with Soldiers and armed men. That their priuiledges confirmed heretofore, are of no power or ſtrength to defend them from theſe euils. And that not onely Diſputations and diuers wreſted interpretations haue beene inuented to diſcredit that profitable buſineſſe of Defence, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken for the profit and good of all; but alſo, that warres are prepared, and great violence done to the Subiect: ſo that it ſeemeth that the bare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of Priuiledges is not now any longer ſufficient to eſtabliſh peace in that Kingdome and thoſe Provinces, but it is neceſſary that what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was promiſed in words, be now ſhewed in deed and action.</p>
            <p>Alſo they doubt not, but that he will be pleaſed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5889:10"/>to remember what a quiet, ſweet and calme ſtate there was thorow the whole kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the other confederate countries, not onely in the dayes of former Kings, his Predeceſſors; but euen at that very time when he was admitted to the ſucceſſion in the ſame kingdome: and how farre it is eſtranged from that tranquility: how much it concerneth the common wealth, that the ancient and wholeſome ordinances of the kingdome, and the old cuſtome be obſerued, not onely about the deſignation, but alſo about the acceptation of the King, whoſoeuer he ſhall bee.</p>
            <p>All which things being duly conſidered; The King and all others may eaſily perceiue, that, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they in times paſt did elect and deſigne him to bee their chiefe Soueraigne Duke, and that of their owne free will and pleaſure, without any eye or regard to the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia:</hi> yet, the caſe with the Kingdom and other prouinces ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo as it doth; they may not to the great preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of others, (as well concerning the execution of the deſignation, as concerning the deſignation it ſelfe) accept and admit him to be their gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
            <p>Alſo that the King by the premiſes may eaſily coniecture, that theſe embroilements and combuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, together with the troubles and hurts which followed thereupon in point of religion through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Sileſia,</hi> cannot be remedied and laid aſleepe, by the bare charter of confirmation of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5889:10"/>priuiledges: but that theſe times deſire to ſee the effect of this confirmation, and doe require deedes and not words.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, they hope, and beſeech his maieſty, that he would be pleaſed not to take it in ill part; that, weighing the great danger of theſe times, they thinke it good for them to expect, vntill he doe not onely vndertake the gouernment and adminiſtration of the kingdome of <hi>Bohemia:</hi> but alſo, ſtinting all theſe troubles, doe ſettle the whole kingdome in that ſtate which their priuiledges doe require, and that they may freely without warre and moleſtation, enioy their priuiledges confirmed. And that this may be done very well, if (all warres being ended) he would <hi>ipſo facto</hi> performe all things to the Prouinces according to the preſcript of their priuiledges in point of Religion, and would take order for them by granting ſuch a charter, that by it they might enioy the peace of Religion. To the performance hereof, he needed not any inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; for here was nothing required but the very effect of their priuiledges; and that is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meanes both to ſettle peace and tranquility on all ſides, and alſo to keepe and retaine it conſtantly: which being vſed, when he ſhould enter vpon the adminiſtration of the kingdome, he needed not to make any queſtion at all, but they in their place will doe what neceſſity requireth.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Earle of <hi>Thorne</hi> his expedition and voyage into the lower <hi>Auſtria,</hi> we haue ſpoken
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5889:11"/>before. The Romiſh Catholiques euen vntill then were in deliberating what anſwer they ſhould giue to the Proteſtants: For the Proteſtants had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded ſeuen articles to them to conſult vpon: namely, that all the R. catholike States in the vpper &amp; lower <hi>Auſtria</hi> ſhould be one body with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in thoſe parts; that in time of vrgent neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity the one ſide ſhould defend the other: that their priuiledges (as well old as new) ſhould remaine whole and entyre to euery ſtate, and nothing in them, ſhould be altered and changed. In burialls and ſpittles for ſicke folke there ſhould be no difference made between Proteſtants &amp; R. Catholiques: but that without reſpect of religion both alike ſhould receiue the like benefite by them. That to the vniuerſity of <hi>Vienna</hi> (which the ſtates by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent, founded in the yeare 1613) learned men ſhould be called without reſpect of what Religion they be, viz. Romiſh Catholique or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant. That no man ſhould be troubled for diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in religion. That both ſides ſhould abſtaine from perſecuting one another, and that euery man ſhould be permitted to enioy his owne liberty.</p>
            <p>And howſoeuer as yet, they could not agree v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the foreſaid articles, yet, becauſe the earle of <hi>Thorne</hi> deſired it, they remoued the gariſon from the city of <hi>Laba:</hi> which being done, <hi>Thorne</hi> placed there a gariſon of his ſouldiers; vntill ſuch time as the States had leuied an army, and prouided a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon for that City.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:5889:11"/>
            <head>The Citie <hi>Tina</hi> taken in by the Earle of Thorne.</head>
            <p>AT the latter end of Iuly the Earle being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided of a very good Army at <hi>Omnitium,</hi> went forth of purpoſe to ioyne battle with Count <hi>Buquoy;</hi> he led after him 46. companies of horſe, and 48. enſignes of foote. But the Count thinking it ſmall adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage to him accept the fight, declined it by all meanes, keeping himſelfe very carefully in his tents: wherefore the Earle made an aſſault vpon the towne of <hi>Tina</hi> and tooke it, and ſo put all the gariſon ſouldiers and the borderers thereabout to the ſword. Not long after ſome of the officers of the Count <hi>Buquoy</hi> (not knowing what had paſſed) came that way, and were inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by the new gariſon the Earle had placed there in the towne.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:5889:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>FERDINAND</hi> His ELECTION, in what manner performed.</head>
            <p>AFter certaine ſeſſions in the Court at <hi>Franc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> betweene the Electors of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality; and the Embaſſadors of the Secular Electors, and that the Biſhop-Electors perceiued that thoſe Embaſſadors could not be wrought v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon to remit any thing of their commiſſion, Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers were diſpatched in all haſt the 24. of Iuly to the principall of the Lay-Electors vnto the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and the <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Rhine.</hi> In the meane while <hi>Ferdinand</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Colein</hi> withdrew themſelues vnto <hi>Lewis Lantzgraue</hi> of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> and ſpent the time in hunting, when they came to <hi>Francford</hi> againe, and aſſembled another Court, it was declared to <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> that he ſhould appeare in the ſame Court againe the 9. of Auguſt to take a ſolemne Oath, which was to be adminiſtred to him by the State and people of <hi>Francford,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as was preſcribed in the <hi>Golden Bull.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:5889:12"/>
            <p>The 8. of Auguſt hauing receiued full reſolution from the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> concerning his more abſolute power, the Magiſtrate preſently cauſed it to be proclamed by ſound of trumpet: that all ſtrangers ſhould depart the City: thoſe onely excepted which belonged to the Court of <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> and the Princes Electors: the next day the Oath was giuen to him in the Court of the Gouernour, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Court gate of all the Citizens and Gariſon Souldiers to the number of a 1000. Afterwards their meetings being continued, diuers conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were debated, till at length the 18. of Auguſt was ſet downe for the Election day to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in their Church.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:5889:13"/>
               <head>The order of going to Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FERDINAND</hi> and the Electors came to the Court in Coaches, and from thence (being Royally apparelled in Electorate Robes) they rode on horſe-backe to the Church of S. <hi>Bartholmew</hi> about eight a clocke in the morning, being enuironed round about with men at armes, the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens being placed on eyther hand.</p>
               <p>Now the Order was this: The Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> and <hi>Trieers</hi> rode firſt; <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> hauing vpon his head a Crown of exceeding great valew, and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Colein,</hi> to aſſociate him, came next; laſt of all followed the Embaſſadours of the ſecular Electors.</p>
               <p>All things being done in the Church about twelue a clocke, they rode backe in this equipage; The Biſhop of <hi>Trieers</hi> went firſt alone by himſelf: next after followed the Embaſſadours of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Electors; firſt, the <hi>Palatines,</hi> with the Globe of the Empire; in the middeſt the Embaſſadour of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> with the Sword; and after him hee of <hi>Brandenburge,</hi> with the Scepter; <hi>Ferdinand</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed theſe alone by himſelfe; and next vnto him rode the Electors of <hi>Colein,</hi> and <hi>Mentz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Election thus ſolemnly performed, Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers were ſtraight ſent to <hi>Aquiſgraue</hi> and <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimberge</hi> to fetch the Crowne, and Scepter, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5889:13"/>other ornaments belonging to the Coronation, which are there kept.</p>
               <p>In the meane time <hi>Lewis Lantzgraue</hi> of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> and the Embaſſadour of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> came to <hi>Francford</hi> to congratulate <hi>Ferdinand.</hi> Then was made the vſuall preparation for the Coronation: a great long Bridge was built, which reached from the Court, all ouer the Market place, to the very Church. Before the Court was a huge ſpacious Kitchin rayſed for the boyling of an Oxe. Then was there a Well artificially contriued, which did ſend forth out of the ground, red and white wine, Barrels and Tubbes to that purpoſe being priuily before conueighed vnder the earth. Another large place was made in the Court for the Imperiall Banquet, Royally furniſhed with much variety, and drinke in wonderfull plenty. Laſt of all, there were ſet vp Theaters and Stages for ſhewes, and a Royall Chayre of State ſet in the Church for the Emperour.</p>
               <p>About the ſame time (being the latter end of <hi>Iuly</hi>) two thouſand <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who had waſted many places of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Auſtria,</hi> with their burning of Townes, and robberies, hauing gotten great booty, and being diſſwaded from ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked attempts by the States of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> withdrew themſelues priuately and went home-ward with all their ſpoyles: and there was a rumour that <hi>Sumadius</hi> an <hi>Hungarian</hi> Captaine, thought to haue followed them with fiue hundred <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:5889:14"/>vnder his owne command: But Count <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoi</hi> getting intelligence thereof, gaue that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in charge to the Cornet of Horſe that lay in <hi>Wallenſtein,</hi> that they ſhould way-lay them at ſome fit paſſage: by which meanes they were preuented, and defeated, all their Bootie taken from them, many of them ſlaine, and the reſt put to flight.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:5889:14"/>
            <head>The Aſſembly of the States of <hi>Morauia,</hi> and their Decrees, fiue in number, for eſtabliſhing the <hi>Confederation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ABout the beginning of this moneth, it was agreed by the States of <hi>Morauia</hi> aſſembled at <hi>Prinna:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 That the Confederation begun of late, and confirmed by a ſolemne Oath betweene the <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians, Morauians, Sileſians,</hi> and <hi>Luſatians,</hi> ſhould be ratified, and all the branches thereof ſhould be kept inuiolably to all ſucceeding Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And to the end they might auenge their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the barbarous and incredible tyranny, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage cruelty which their enemies had exerciſed vpon them; beſides the Souldiers which were alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in gariſon, there ſhould be preſſed 1500. more and <hi>Ralph a Schlenitz</hi> ſhould be their commander.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It was decreed likewiſe that the Edict touching ſuch as were proſcribed for their bad and treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous gouernment ſhould be baniſhed the country for euer, and their goods to be ceized to the vſe of the towne where they dwelt, and to that purpoſe to be ſold to the beſt aduantage, made by the States
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5889:15"/>a little before aſſembled in the ſame place, ſhould ſtill be ratified and confirmed.</p>
            <p n="4">4 They haue profeſſed publiquely, and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they cannot with a ſafe Conſcience be help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the States neither in men nor money, vnleſſe all the Eccleſiaſticall goods of Friers and Nunnes bee ſequeſtred from them and giuen to the States, and might be ſold from the good of the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth without al let or contradiction of any man: and that prouiſion ſhould be made out of this eſtate and goods thus alienated &amp; ſold from the Abbyes, Prelates, ouer-ſeers, Friers and Nunnes of what order ſoeuer, as alſo from ſuch as refuſing the ſtate of mariage, freely chooſe to remaine in that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſingle life ſtill: and that after a fitting and competent ſtate during their liues.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That there ſhould be a diligent ſearch made of Armes laid vp in any houſes, Monaſteries, Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neries ſituate as well within the City, as without, and that thoſe Armes, together with all gold, ſiluer and moneyes found in the hand of any Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call perſon to be taken from them, and to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated with the publique good: and that all Citizens and ſubiects of the Romiſh Catholique Religion, together with all partakers of the Roman faction; ſhould be laid hold on, and their houſes being care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſearched, all Armes ſhould be taken from them, and be conueied to a certaine place appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5889:15"/>for them. And foraſmuch as they haue their Gouernor, and inferiour Officers alſo in ſuſpition, and cannot repoſe that truſt in them which is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to men of that place, they ſhall giue vp their account of the gouernment of their ſeuerall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces to deputies aſſigned and authoriſed to that effect: and in caſe there be neceſſity and deſert, they ſhall be diſplaced from their offices, others of the Proteſtants being choſen in their roome.</p>
            <p>And that hee might reſtraine them, and force the <hi>Bohemians</hi> to breake off their Confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the calling backe of his Armie, enters againe into their Countrey with eight hundred horſe, and foote; and hauing got into his poſſeſſion a very ſtrong fort called <hi>Ioſuit,</hi> determined alſo to take in the Caſtle of the Prince of <hi>Lichtenſtein,</hi> and ſo at once to open himſelf a paſſage into the whole Country, but the States of <hi>Morania</hi> preuented him, and recouered the Caſtle into their owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection before, and placed a very ſtrong Gariſon in it: when he ſaw himſelfe diſappointed, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued new forces out of <hi>Hungary,</hi> he made attempt vpon the gouernment of <hi>Diffenbacchius,</hi> and when he found him well appointed, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſpoiled and fired ſome poore villages in the frontires of it, hee turned himſelfe to a towne called <hi>Niclasburge,</hi> but receiued a repulſe there to, by valiant reſiſtance of the Gariſon hee was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to leaue them with no ſmall loſſe to his men.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:5889:16"/>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, the <hi>Morauians</hi> incenſed with theſe moleſtations, hauing leuied 1500. of their owne countrimen, and ioyned with them ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forraine Aide, marcht directly to meete him, and when they found him, Auguſt the 8. day, lying in <hi>Viſtrie</hi> with 9000 horſe and foote, preſently he fell a skirmiſhing with them, and forced him, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing many of his men dead in the place, from the narrow ſtraight into the Champion Fields. Now he little thought that the <hi>Morauians</hi> would proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the fight, but they all on fire with rage and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, ſet ſo valiantly vpon him, that the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes was prolonged and continued ſixe houres to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. <hi>Tampire</hi> loſt 2000. of his foote and horſe, and laſt of all was driuen by his flight to leaue the <hi>Morauians</hi> the glory of the Field and day. During this fight, the Earle of <hi>Monte-cuculi, Saxo</hi> of <hi>Lauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge</hi> were mortally wounded &amp; many with them, and not long after died of the hurts there receiued. In the heat of the conflict the <hi>Morauians</hi> were who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mingled with the <hi>Tampirians:</hi> the Smoake and Duſt had cauſed ſo great darkenes that they could not know one another, that it could be nothing leſſe then a miracle, that but 300 of the <hi>Morauians</hi> were ſlaine, and as many wounded, in ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion: and thus <hi>Tampire</hi> was compelled to forſake <hi>Morauia,</hi> and to write to <hi>Vienna,</hi> for new ſupplyes, to be ſent vnto him,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:5889:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Fort of Vechin taken by</hi> BVQVOI.</head>
            <p>COunt <hi>Buquoi</hi> meane while is not idle, but ſets vpon the Fort <hi>Vechin</hi> and ſpoiles the little towne belonging to it with 15. ſmall villages, and burnes them to the ground, and when he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood Coronel <hi>Francus</hi> to march that way with 1200. Musketers, he laid 8000. men in ambuſh to entrap him, but <hi>Francus</hi> hauing ſeaſonable intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of ſo great trechery, turned aſide to <hi>Thabor,</hi> and ſo fortunately avoided the danger.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:5889:17"/>
            <head>FREDERICKE <hi>V.</hi> Count <hi>PALATINE</hi> Elector, <hi>choſen King of</hi> Bohemia.</head>
            <p>NOtwithſtanding the Directors for <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the 19. of Auguſt, together with the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of <hi>Morauia, Sileſia, Luſatia</hi> the higher and the lower being preſent, held a Councell from nine in the morning till three in the afternoone, hauing the doores faſt ſhut and lockt vnto them: in which they finally decreed, that <hi>Ferdinand</hi> was to be abdicated and depoſed from his Kingdome, and neuer to be admitted to the ſame, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee choſen in his ſtead: which Decree was publiſhed and proclaimed of the <hi>Bohemians</hi> at three a clocke the ſame day: of the <hi>Sileſians</hi> and <hi>Luſatians</hi> the 21. day of the ſame Moneth: on the 24. and 25. dayes of the ſame Moneth, all the people aſſembled in their Churches, for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and ſolemne prayer to God, that he would direct them in electing a King fitting to gouerne them, and Sermons alſo were made to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>On the 26. of Auguſt, they met againe, and after prayers and other diuine Seruice finiſhed, <hi>Fredericke</hi> Elector <hi>Palatine</hi> by the greater number was choſen and proclaimed King of <hi>Bohemia:</hi> he
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5889:17"/>had voyces to the Election, of the Nobilitie 36 of the Gentry 91. theſe for the preſent: all the free Cities and States for the moſt part conſented to it the next day. Beſides, the hands of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours for <hi>Morauia, Sileſia,</hi> and <hi>Euſatia,</hi> being gathered, it was manifeſtly found, that they were all directed to the <hi>Palatine</hi> with one conſent.</p>
            <p>The Solemnitie was thus performed: The Song of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was ſung, the Bels rung, the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſhot off fiue times together. Embaſſadours alſo being deputed, who the next day ſhould beare the newes to the Elector <hi>Palatine</hi> of this his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection to be King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> by the ioynt voyces of the whole Kingdome, and the three vnited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces before ſpoken off.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:5889:18"/>
            <head>Piſſera ſurpriſed by aſſault of Count Buquoi.</head>
            <p>WHile theſe things were a doing at <hi>Prage, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoi</hi> marched towards <hi>Piſsera</hi> with his whole army, and conſumed the Suburbs with fire. After, he ſent a Trumpet to <hi>Hacquius</hi> commander of two Enſignes in the City, to will him to depart the towne, &amp; yeeld it vp to him. The Captain refuſing, anſwered, <hi>he would fight for his City vntill his lateſt breath, as was the part of a true Souldier. Buquoi</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged with this anſwer, commanded the towne to be aſſaulted in foure ſeuerall places at once: in which conflict though the Gariſon behaued them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues valiantly, and ſlew many, yet at laſt number preuailing, the City was taken by force. After their forſt entrance they ranged vp and downe like mad men. The Captaine was hanged vp, the Gouernor ſlaine with the ſword, great booty was taken, with Engines, and two Rammes for battery, which Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Mansfield</hi> had formerly vſed againſt the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Pilſna.</hi> He withdrew his forces backe toward <hi>Straconitium,</hi> which towne he had alſo a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore brought vnder his power. He thought withall to haue beſieged <hi>Pilſna.</hi> The <hi>Bohemians</hi> followed the Count, but durſt not ſettle vpon him, march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in goodly equipage with a full army: about the ſame time, many fled from <hi>Veraucum</hi> and other places to <hi>Prage,</hi> carrying with them their wiues, children and all their eſtates, being ſtrucken with the terrour of this bloudy maſſacre and cruelty.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:5889:18"/>
            <head>THE CORONATION <hi>of</hi> FERDINAND, <hi>perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> at Francford. Auguſt. 30. 1619.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E ſpake before of the Election of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> to be Emperor: now for as much as it ſeemed good to his Maieſtie, following therein the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and preſident of the Emperor <hi>Matthias</hi> deceaſed, that he himſelfe would alſo be crowned at <hi>Francford;</hi> he ſent and ſought from <hi>Aquiſgrane</hi> and <hi>Norimberge</hi> the Banners, Robes and other ornaments of the Empire; and thus all things neceſſary to this royall ſolemnity were prepared, as wee haue touched before: when the appointed day for the Coronation was come, which was the 30. of Auguſt, according to the old account and the 9. of September according to the new, two daies before, <hi>Lewis Lantzgraue</hi> of <hi>Heſſe</hi> came thither with his two ſonnes, and his brother <hi>Philip:</hi> The day before the ſolemnity approched the Ambaſſadors of <hi>Norimberge,</hi> with the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall crowne and other royall ornaments: The
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5889:19"/>gates were opened to none; the gariſon ſouldiers ſtood in the valley, and the citizens in armes were ſet in euery corner of the ſtreets, but moſt of all from the Court to the Colledge of Electors, and from thence on both ſides the bridge euen to the Church of Saint <hi>Bartholomew:</hi> the middle of the weeke the Ecleſiaſticall Electors went to the Church apart euery one by themſelues; and there putting off their Electorall habits, attired them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues like Biſhops as they were, and in that ſort waited for <hi>Ferdinands</hi> comming, who about 8. of the clock, mounted on a gallant horſe: rode vnto the Temple in this prince-like order: There went before him on foote a great trayne of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Counſellors, and other noble perſonages: the two ſonnes of <hi>Lewis Lantzgraue</hi> of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> and after them <hi>Lewis</hi> their Father, with his brother <hi>Philip,</hi> rode in front together; fiue officers fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed next, and the Ambaſſadors of the three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Electors, who carried before <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Globe, Scepter and Sword of the Empire: <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> himſelfe apparelled like an Elector, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a crowne vpon his head, was carried on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe vnder a canopy, which was borne vp by two noble men (Conſuls) <hi>Daniell Stalburger</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Orthius,</hi> and foure Senators, or ſtates of <hi>Franc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford;</hi> their names were <hi>Iohn-Philip Weiſius, Hierom Stephens, Iohn-Stephens Schadaeus,</hi> and <hi>Iohn-Philip Orthius:</hi> As ſoone as they were come to the Church, the Eccleſiaſticall Electors, in their <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificalibus;</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:5889:19"/>together with their Suffraganes and ſome others of the Clergy, aduanced forward to meete <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> from the Quire euen to the doore of the Temple, &amp; hauing receiued him ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norably, they lead him to an Altar ſituate at the entrance of the Quire or Chancell: There he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into a ſeate appointed for prayer, placed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Altar, made of cloth of ſiluer, and a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopy of the ſame coſtly ſtuffe let downe from the roofe of the Church ouer the ſeate: the two Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops alſo went into their ſeuerall ſeates, on the right hand <hi>Triers,</hi> on the left <hi>Colein,</hi> prepared for them &amp; richly hung with red Scarlet cloth: <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> tooke vp a little booke which was layd in that ſeate, and compoſed himſelfe to prayer, the Secular Ambaſſadors ſeated alſo neere him: The <hi>Chantors</hi> meane while ſang that ſong: <hi>Glory be to God on high:</hi> the Elector of <hi>Mentz</hi> began Maſſe, and in the ſaying of it the other Electors and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors lead away <hi>Ferdinand</hi> to the high Altar, and from thence (after Benediction) vnto a royall Throne, which was placed a ſtep or two aboue the ſeate where <hi>Ferdinand</hi> prayed; continuing their obſeruancy and ceremonies, he came to the Altar againe, and there fell vpon his knees, the Electors and the Ambaſſadors kneeling by him till the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany was ſaid ouer him. This done, Hee that was to Conſecrate him, propounded to him the vſuall Queſtions. <hi>Whether He would ſtedfaſtly keepe the Chriſtian and Catholique Religion, defend the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5889:20"/>Church, adminiſter iuſtice to all, encreaſe, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the Empire, maintaine the widdows and father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe children, render due honour to the Biſhop of Rome: Ferdinand</hi> anſwered affirmatiuely to euery of theſe, and confirmed his affirmation with a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne oath. The Conſecrator turned himſelfe to the Electors, Ambaſſadors, and all the people ſtanding round about, demaunded of them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would ſubmit themſelues to <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> eſtabliſh his kingdome, and performe odedience to his commandements: when they had teſtified their conſents to all thoſe motions, and cryed with a loud voice, <hi>That he ought to be their King;</hi> hee was vnclothed in certaine places of his body, and then the Conſecrator came to him, and taking oyle annointed the Crowne of his head, his neck, his breaſts, his right arme and his hands, adding theſe words at each ſeuerall part hee annointed; <hi>I annoint thee with holy oyle, in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vnction finiſhed, the Eccleſiaſticall Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, with their Suffraganes leade <hi>Ferdinand</hi> through the Quire into the Conclaue or Colledge of Election, and hauing wiped off the oyle, they put vpon him the ancient Emperiall and Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall Robes brought from <hi>Norimbergh;</hi> that is, the Bootes and long Surpliſſe, and Gowne let downe from his necke by his Breſt in parts and ſo throwne ouer his ſhoulders, they put alſo Gloues vpon his hands, and thus attired as it were a Deacon, they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5889:20"/>bring him forth againe from the Chancell to the ſeate where he firſt prayed, and there the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crator liberally beſtowed vpon him a new bleſſing; prayers ſaid, <hi>Ferdinand</hi> aſcends into the Imperiall Throne, and the Electors of <hi>Triers</hi> and <hi>Colein</hi> take downe the ſword of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great from the Altar, where together with the Crowne and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it was layd; draw it forth, and giue it into <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinands</hi> hands, the Conſecrator ſpeaking theſe words: <hi>Take this ſword by the hands of Biſhops.</hi> And when he comes to theſe words: <hi>Be thou girt with this ſword, &amp;c.</hi> Then the ſword is put vp into the ſheath againe, and girt vnto his ſide by the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of the Emperiall Electors.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, after this the Conſecrator takes the Ring from the Altar, and pronouncing certaine words put it vpon his finger: from the ſame Altar he takes the Scepter and Globe of the Empire, and giues them into his hand; the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his right hand, the Globe into his left, with theſe words: <hi>Take the rod of Vertue &amp; Equity;</hi> laſt of all, the Emperiall Crowne is lifted off the Altar and ſet vpon his head by the three Spirituall Electors ioyntly, with theſe words: <hi>take the crowne of the Kingdome,</hi> and then they array him with the golden cloke of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great; theſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies obſerued, he comes down from his Throne, &amp; deliuers back theſe things to the Ambaſſadors of the Temporall Electors, that is to ſay, the Globe to the <hi>Palatines</hi> Ambaſſador, and the Scepter to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5889:21"/>
               <hi>Brandenburghs,</hi> and ſo of the reſt; then againe hee makes towards the Altar, and there takes a ſolemne oath, that hee will doe all thoſe things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to a good Emperor.</p>
            <p>The oath taken, the Maſſe goes on, <hi>Ferdinand</hi> betaking him to his throne the while, and here is exquiſit muſicke playd by the Quire: From the Throne he is once more led to the Altar, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſſe firſt offered, Hee receiues the Sacrament at the hands of the Conſecrators; the Sacrament, prayers and other ſeruice fully fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, the Conſecrator <hi>Mentz</hi> goes out firſt, <hi>Triers</hi> and <hi>Colein</hi> after him; and betweene them goes <hi>Ferdinand</hi> to a ſtately Theater, a ſtage rayſed vp aloft towards the South, hung on all ſides with rich Tapiſtry and Stamell cloth; being layd ouer the floore therof: before him are caried the Armes of the Empire by the Ambaſſadors of the Secular Electors; the Suffraganes and others of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy following after: there the Spirituall Electors place him in a Princely Throne, eleuated ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what aboue the reſt of the ſtage, couered ouer with cloth of gold, and hung with a Canopy of red Veluet, the Chanters at the time ſinging the ſong of Saint <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> The Muſicke ceaſing, the Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> drawes neere to <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand,</hi> and in his owne name, and in the name of the other Electors, congratulates to him this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Inauguration, and withall, excellently and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully commends to him the whole Empire.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:5889:21"/>
            <p>Preſently vpon this the Archbiſhop of <hi>Triers</hi> and <hi>Colein,</hi> and all the Clergy leaue the ſtage and returne into the Chancell, where putting off their <hi>Pontificalibus,</hi> they put vpon them againe the robes of the Electors: <hi>Ferdinand</hi> ſtaies ſtill in his Chaire of ſtate, and creates Knights, by ſtriking them with the ſword of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great. After this Hee riſes vp, and goes himſelfe out of the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ater, and returnes from Church in this ſolemne order.</p>
            <p>Firſt and formoſt goe the ſeruants of the Court, next the Counſellors of the Emperor, and the Princes Electors, as alſo a very great number of noble perſonages, then followed the Earles and Barons: in the next ranke the Archbiſhop of <hi>Triers</hi> by himſelfe, the <hi>Palatines</hi> delegate and <hi>Brandenburghs</hi> together, carying the Globe, and the Scepter, then the Delegate of <hi>Saxony</hi> alone carying the Sword, next the Emperor with the Crowne on his head, and the Emperiall robes on his backe, by himſelfe likewiſe vnder a Canopy borne by the States of <hi>Francford,</hi> as was ſhewed before: The Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> and <hi>Colein</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, all going backe on foote cloſed vp this royall Traine.</p>
            <p>Thus goe they along forwards ſtraight to the Court ouer the bridge couered ouer with Stamell: there followed a little after three of <hi>Ferdinands</hi> Chaplaines on horſe-back which caſt abrode mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the people, gold and ſiluer, of leſſe and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5889:22"/>greater valew of round and ſquare faſhion: the greater money on one ſide had an arme ſtretched forth of the Cloud, holding in the hand a Kingly Crowne with this inſcription, TO THOSE THAT STRIVE LAWFVLLY: on the other ſide this, FERDINAND II. KING OF HVNGARY AND BOHEMIA, CROWNED KING OF THE RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANS SEPTEMBER IX. MDCXIX. The leſſer moneys had the letter F. with a crowne, and the number of 11. ſtamped on them on the one ſide; on the other a Crowne, and theſe words: CROWNED KING OF THE ROMANS, SEP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEMBER IX. MDCXIX.</p>
            <p>The caſting of this money made ſuch a hurly burly among the Common-people, that the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines could ſcarce make way for the greatneſſe of the preſſe, though they were on horſebacke: the cloth on the bridge as ſoone as the Emperor paſſed, was cut, torne and rent in peeces by the people.</p>
            <p>In the Pallace or Hall of the Court, the Tables were ſet and royally furniſhed for himſelfe and the Princes Electors: the Tables of the three Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Electors were couered with red Veluet as alſo the Table of the Elector of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> but no meate was ſet vpon them, as is prouided by the conſtitution of the golden Bull: being thus at laſt in the Pallace, the Delegates of the Secular Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors addreſſed them to performe the Offices of the Electorſhip, in ſtead of their Lords and Princes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5889:22"/>themſelues. When <hi>Pappenhemius</hi> the heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Marſhall of the Empire mounted his horſe, and being brought with a meaſure of ſiluer, to a heape of oates, being laid together in the open yard, before the Court, betweene the Well of wine and the Kitchin, filled his meaſure, and ſtrucke it with a rod of ſiluer, and then gaue it to a Seruant to keepe, the people after ſnatching them away.</p>
            <p>After him appeared one of the Delegates of the <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> riding alſo on horſe-backe from the Court, and tooke vp a Baſen of ſiluer with an Ewer of gold, and a Towell, ſet vpon a Board by the Kitchin where the Bull was roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and carryed it with him to the Court.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, the Delegate of the Elector <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> Sewer hereditary to the Kingdome, being brought foorth from the Court, tooke certaine diſhes of the Bull roaſted in the publique Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, couered with foure ſiluer platters, and ſet out on the Dreſſer, and bore them with him to the Court.</p>
            <p>This being done, the rude multitude breaking into the Kitchin, by maine force carryed away with them the Bull which was roaſted whole, with the head, feet, hoofes, tayle and hornes, and ſtuft full of Hares, Conies, Lambes, Geeſe, and diuers other ſorts of Birds and fowles, pulling it by peece-meale, and cutting it a ſunder with
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5889:23"/>their kniues: and which is more rude, they defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Kitchin, and tooke away all the Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of it.</p>
            <p>While they kept this coyle, <hi>Ferdinand</hi> and the Electors are euery one at their owne Tables. The Well before the Court, made in the manner of a rocke, beganne to flow with redde and white wine, out of the mouth of an Eagle with two heads crowned, which was placed betweene two Lyons bearing the Ornaments of the Empire, the Scepter, the Globe and Sword.</p>
            <p>Now the wine ranne out of this Eagle in great abundance for three houres together, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into two veſſels of exceeding great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie, as many as would hauing liberty to draw and drinke of it as much as they would, till at laſt, by the rage of the giddy multitude, they in vaine ſtriuing againſt them who were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to keepe it, the Well was borne downe, and the Eagle, with the Lions, and all other Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of it were caryed away.</p>
            <p>The Royall Dinner continued till fiue of the clocke in the after-noone with great ſolemnitie and ioy. The Emperour at laſt departed from that Court to his owne Royall Palace, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors accompanying him ſome few dayes after. There were publique Tiltings for ioy of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation.</p>
            <p>After it the Ambaſſadours of the <hi>Palatine</hi> and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5889:23"/>
               <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and laſt of all, of the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> returned home to their ſeuerall Princes, many wiſhing all proſperitie and good ſucceſſe to the Emperour, and expreſſing their prayers for him in Verſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
